Some of the most common
questions I get
are about the dosage
and type of vitamin B12.
Check out the video
for some answers.
"The Optimal Vitamin B12 Dosage and Type"
Universal improvement of B12 status
appears “to be a nutritional
imperative with possibly
profound beneficial effects,”
particularly at the bookends
of life—at old age and infancy.
I’ve explained the rationale
for my recommendations
to take vitamin B12 supplements
once a week or once a day,
or alternately eat sufficient
daily B12-fortified foods.
But for those over age 65 those
guidelines go out the window.
The recommendations change
to everyone taking
a high daily dose of
1,000 mcg every day.
Starting at age 50 everyone,
meat-eaters and vegans alike,
should be taking B12 supplements
or eating B12-fortified foods.
But over age 65, 50 a day may not do it.
Even 100 a day doesn’t seem sufficient.
Researchers investigated three
doses and found that most
didn’t normalize their MMA until
after the 1,000 microgram dose.
(MMA suppression is a
measure of B12 sufficiency.)
But they just tested 25, 100, and 1,000.
Maybe 250 or 500 would do it?
Researchers set out to find an
adequate dose at that age,
and it seems we need at least about
650 to 1,000 a day in most people,
hence my 1,000 a day
recommendation after age 65.
OK, what about the other
end of the life cycle?
The consequences of B12 deficiency
and insufficiency can be
devastating in
infancy and childhood,
and this is not just a problem
for plant-based pregnancies.
“Vitamin B-12 insufﬁciency during
pregnancy is common
even in nonvegetarian populations.”
About a quarter of all pregnant
women aren’t getting enough B12,
and that number rises to nearly
one in three by the third trimester.
But, insufficiency isn’t as
bad as frank deficiency,
which can manifest in
cases like cerebral atrophy,
meaning brain shrinkage,
in a “Vitamin B12-deficient
Infant of a Vegetarian Mother.”
Thankfully, even severe
brain atrophy can be
substantially reversed with
B12 supplementation,
but better not to become
deficient in the first place.
The solution proposed by a group
of French pediatricians
is to recommend against
raising vegan kids at all,
since B12 supplementation is
necessary. And they’re not alone.
To vegan or not to vegan.
In 2016, two professional
organizations, the U.S. Academy
of Nutrition and Dietetics and
the German Nutrition Society,
issued conﬂicting statements.
The U.S. Academy said that
even strictly plant-based diets
are appropriate for all
stages of the life cycle,
whereas the German group
echoed the French group,
saying since you have to take B12
we can’t recommend a vegan diet
for pregnant women, lactating women,
infants, children, or adolescents.
To confuse the matter further,
the American Academy of Pediatrics
appeared to have it both ways;
in one place repeating
the U.S. Academy’s position, while
in another place it stated that
vegan diets should not
be recommended for children.
But I think they’re just
saying the same thing.
Everyone agrees that a non-B12
supplemented plant-based diet
is a bad idea—that’s part of what
the U.S. Academy means
by “well-planned.”
Everyone eating plant-based,
but especially pregnant
and breastfeeding women, must
ensure a regular, reliable source
of vitamin B12, meaning B12
supplements or B12-fortified foods.
But then you may be able to
get the best of both worlds.
That’s why there are
reviews with titles like this:
plant-based pregnancies:
danger or panacea?
Danger if you don’t take your B12,
but “following a plant-[based] diet
during pregnancy may be protective
against the development of preeclampsia,
pre-gravid obesity, and minimize the
exposure to [DNA-damaging] agents.”
It may also protect our newborns
“from the onset of pediatric diseases,
such as pediatric wheezing,
diabetes, neural tube defects,
orofacial clefts, and some
pediatric tumors.”
“Vegan pregnant women
have a lower-than-average
rate of cesarean section,
less postpartum depression,
and lower neonatal and
maternal mortality,
with no complications or negative
outcomes that are higher than average.”
In addition, a lower incidence
of what used to be called toxemia,
a potentially dangerous pregnancy
complication known as preeclampsia.
“Overall, plant-based diets
seem to confer protection to both
mothers and newborns” by not
only “reducing the risk of several
pregnancy-related issues”, but
decreasing the risk of childhood disease.
“Children following plant-based
diets might have a lower risk
of developing obesity,” obviously
are less exposed to drugs
used in animal production,
and a favorable
anti-inﬂammatory proﬁle
of cell-signaling factors.
But again, everyone on a plant-based
diet has to get enough B12.
Pregnant and breastfeeding
women can just follow
my 50 micrograms a day
recommendation for nonpregnant adults,
or 2,000 a week, though they
suggest breaking up those doses
into two halves to boost absorption.
After infants are weaned, they
can start on 5 micrograms a day;
from ages 4 through 10 they can
take half the adult dose of 25 a day;
and then at age 11 they can
take 50 a day or 2,000 a week.
You don’t have to worry
about taking too much.
It’s water-soluble and you’ll
just end up with expensive pee.
I've talked about the optimal dose of
vitamin B12 supplements for adults,
as well as in childhood, pregnancy,
and old age to prevent
vitamin B12 deficiency. But
what if you already have it?
How much do you
have to take to treat it?
Your doctor might want you
to get vitamin B12 injections,
but oral B12, even for those
who can't absorb it well,
has long been considered one
of medicine's best kept secrets.
It's now considered well-known that
orally administered B12 supplements
are as effective in overcoming deficiency
states as intramuscular injections
when you get up to taking
1,000 micrograms a day.
How long do you have
to take 1,000 a day for?
It depends on how low
your levels start out.
Because B12 status in
pregnancy is so critical,
there is a suggestion that plant-based
women get it checked
throughout pregnancy and to adjust
supplementation as necessary.
This is how much you
should take if you're low.
Note the recommendations for
pregnant and breast-feeding women
are the same as everyone
else over the age of 10.
So if you're a teen or adult diagnosed
with vitamin B12 deficiency,
you'd take 1,000 micrograms
a day for one to four months,
depending on how low you
start out, before going back
to a regular maintenance dose
of 50 a day or 2,000 a week,
with toddlers and small
children taking smaller doses.
There are two main types on the
market though: methylcobalamin,
marketed as methyl B12,
and cyanocobalamin,
typically marketed as
just vitamin B12.
Methyl is more expensive so
it must be better, right?
Wrong. Cyanocobalamin is the most
used form due to its high stability.
See, methylcobalamin is less
stable than cyanocobalamin,
and it is particularly susceptible
to photodecomposition,
meaning destruction from
being exposed to light.
There's no advantage to using the
light-sensitive forms of cobalamin,
such as methyl B12, instead of the
stable cyano forms, which are readily
converted in the body into the type
you need, where you need it.
The one major exception
may be kidney failure though.
Methylcobalamin may be better for
those with impaired kidney function.
It's been speculated that oral
methylcobalamin or injected
hydroxycobalamin may also
be preferable in smokers,
though it has yet to be confirmed.
Because methylcobalamin is less
stable, you'd probably want to take
much higher doses. So for example,
in those with kidney failure, you'd be
taking one to two thousand micrograms
a day, compared to just 50 micrograms
of cyanocobalamin in someone
with normal kidney function.
Another reason to use the
cyanocobalamin, as opposed to
the more expensive kinds, is that it has
a track record of safety and efficacy,
whereas, for example, in one study
even up to 2,000 micrograms a day
of methylcobalamin wasn't enough
to correct vitamin B12 deficiency
in one of three vegans
they tested it on.
The bottom line is that so-called
coenzyme forms of B12,
like methyl B12 and adenyl B12,
also known as adenosyl B12,
are not likely to be superior to
cyanocobalamin, which is more stable.
Cyanocobalamin appears to be best
suited for oral supplementation,
which is why I specify its
use in my recommendations.
Note I also recommend ideally
taking it separately
as a chewable, sublingual,
or liquid supplement.
Why can't you just get it as part
of a multivitamin or something?
Because various vitamins and
minerals mixed into the same pill
can destroy active B12, forming B12
analogues—B12-look-alikes that (not)
only can our body not use, the
analogues can be potentially harmful
because they can inhibit the
transport of what little B12 is left.
That's why using multivitamins
can even be counterproductive
for the supplementation of vitamin
B12. And this isn't just in theory.
There was a tragic case of severe
vitamin B12 deficiency in an infant
born to a vegan mother who thought
she was doing everything right
taking a multivitamin
that contained B12,
though it may have also just
been inadequate dose.
Why chewable or sublingual?
Absorption is boosted when
the B12 mixes with saliva,
since you secrete a B12 binding
protein from your salivary glands
that helps transport B12 safely
through the digestive tract.
Having people chew a tablet of B12 and
their B12 levels go up 10 times more
than just simply swallowing the
exact same pill. Check it out.
Vegans boosted out of deficiency
chewing a B12 supplement,
but nothing in those who
just swallowed it whole.
Maybe they had some sort of
absorption problem or something?
No, because then if you tell them
to start chewing it instead
of swallowing it whole, their
levels shoot right up as well.
In my latest book How Not to Diet,
I suggest a third option to B12-
fortified foods and supplements:
brushing twice daily with
a B12-fortified toothpaste,
specifically this brand,
which was put to the test
in two double-blind,
randomized, placebo-controlled studies.
Participants were instructed to use
the toothpaste two times a day
for two minutes at a time, and indeed,
were able to correct the markers
of B12 insufficiency in the blood
of vegans and among the elderly,
but that was on average. Unfortunately,
it didn't work in every last person,
which is why it's not included
in my recommendations.
Though, look, if you get your levels
tested before and after brushing
for a few months and they go up, then
you could presumably stick with it.
In summary, vitamin B12 deficiency
is not to be messed around with,
with the potential to cause a wide
range of disorders of the gut,
blood, brain, and
nervous system.
With the ever-increasing demand
for cleanliness in our food chain—
which is a very good thing—
it is of special importance that we
secure a regular reliable source,
and the safest, cheapest, healthiest
source is B12 supplements
or green-light B12-fortified foods.